every athlete at the top of the strength
game at the top of the aesthetic
physique game they're all using it if
you're not utilizing Tempo training
you're leaving a lot on the table both
when it comes to strength and when it
comes to hypertrophy if you are
proficient in the stones that is a
pretty large Advantage knowing that the
stones typically are going to be the
tiebreaker it's always interesting to
see that to see how like they get
affected by the things that should give
them Advantage right like for
crossfitters a disadvantage is more rest
sometimes
welcome to strength weekly the weekly
show that keeps you updated on
everything from around the barbell game
and the atlas Stones game and the circus
dumbbells game and the pull-up bar game
I'm probably missing something for Barb
ben.com I'm David Thomas Tow and I am
joined by the
incomparable the only adjective I would
use to describe him Phil blechman and
before we get into our intensely packed
show packed with muscle and protein that
is is make sure you subscribe to barbend
on
youtube.com let's talk about the Run of
show we have a number of new world
champions in the strongman game because
the official strongman games as
concluded Laura horbath wins the
Hungarian National weightlifting
championships in her weight category we
also talk about Russell orhei remember
him he's back chopping at the bit for
potentially a third world Championship
next year and we're bringing you a
weekly strength tip at the end of the
show to maybe be more like Russell but
also maybe not because that guy is super
human Phil how are you feeling today I'm
feeling great I'm ready to talk some
strongman there was a lot of close
competitions at the official strongman
games and it was heated all the way
around he heated heated okay Phil uh
question for you uh what is your
favorite strong man event I really enjoy
the atlas Stones over the I should say
the stone off Atlas Stones I like seeing
athletes go head-to-head until they
can't anymore I I think that like that
is really a display of strength and
endurance and I really enjoy that event
it's always takes place during high
stakes and I love that kind of event
okay Phil if you could go back in time
and pluck anyone out from history to be
a commentator for strongman events with
you who would it
be uh I would say have you ever listened
to Jr and pro wrestling by God I can't
believe it it's the steel chair like can
you imagine him being like by God it's
Brian Shaw with the stones that would be
incredible all right because my answer
to that is also from the world of pro
wrestling it's Randy Savage yeah oh yeah
yeah you're like like just imagine
imagine that every event it it works it
works every event okay let's talk about
the official strongman games Phil when
did it happen where did it take place
and by the way what the heck because
this is a family-friendly show are the
official strongman
games so the official strongman games
feature uh strongman and strong women
competition it took place this year
December 1st through the 3rd in
Charleston West Virginia and it
highlights all of the uh weight classes
beyond the open so you get uh women's
under 64 kilograms and under 73
kilograms 82 kilograms and on the men's
side you get at under 80 kilograms under
90 kilograms you get the 105 kogam
championships as well so we get to see
the weight classes for both strong men
and strong women at the official strong
men games which is really exciting
because you get to see a different kind
of athlete performing strong man events
all right so it's it's considered the
world championships for those lighter
categories what about for the open
categories the super heavyweight
athletes if you will not that that's a
term in strongman but like basically the
Unlimited weight categories in
weightlifting we call them like the
super Heavies right or in powerlifting
the super Heavies what does this
competition mean for them because that
is those weight classes are actually
still contested here even though they're
not considered the world championships
yeah so there is a men's open uh
competition that takes place at the
official strongman games and that one
really acts that particular division
acts really as a qualifier for giants
live so this year spoiler Marcus Crowder
he won the men's open division which
means that he is now qualified to
compete on the Giants live circuit and
if you uh Podium at a giants live event
that qualifies you for the world's
strongest man competition which will
take place in 2024 obviously I think
something has really interesting too
this took place in Charleston West
Virginia spoiler alert I lived there for
a little bit when I was a kid if you
were ever uh homesick from school about
15 or so years ago and you were watching
the world's strongest man back then it
was the metric's World's Strongest Man I
believe on ESPN 2 the dose you might
have seen it in Charleston West Virginia
so a fun little fact what are a few
performances that stood out to you Phil
so ran love continues to dominate in the
under 64 kilogram category so she won
here that's no surprise that was
expected going in uh we see Andrea
Thomson she won the matches over 40
former uh world's strongest woman very
obvious and expected to see her do well
here as well Aaron Murray is actually uh
been putting up some really big results
in the past year she competed with Team
USA at the world's strongest Nation
competition she won the America's
strongest woman contest in her weight
class Rebecca Roberts in the women's
open that was actually a really close
competition between her and Lucy
underdown they tied on points and it
came down to uh uh Rebecca Roberts
having a better Atlas Stone performance
which functioned as the tiebreaker it
really was a lot of close competitions
all the way down all all of the
divisions Mark Felix won the match was
over 50 H won the Masters over 40 and
then Marcus Crow of course he wins the
men's open he get he qualifies for
giants live competition and we'll likely
see a lot of him uh in 2024 the other
thing I want to point out uh tiebreakers
we talked about tiebreakers Atlas
stones that has become and it has been
for a while but I just want to remind
folks that that's often the tiebreaker
if folks are tied in points in Strongman
Competition look it's strongman you know
you're going to see Stones right that's
kind of become something that's been
codified I think in the last six to
seven years that's not necessarily weird
that's not something that's super
controversial at this point right it
goes to show you that in a sport where
you can have literally anything you
might be asked to move any number of
strange objects right it is a sport that
is known for being somewhat
unpredictable and odd right because
that's half the
fun the constant is you know stones are
going to be there right a certain
competition you also know deadlifts
might be there you might know you might
like putting weight overhead is also
going to be there but there are always
variations on that right Stones stones
are always going to be there and I think
that it's NE to have a constant in a
sport that also has variability right
and I think that athletes know if they
want to perform at the highest level in
the sport of
strongman they're all there's always
room to improve and always reason to
train your Atlas Stone loading I agree I
think that there is something to be said
that if you are proficient in the stones
that going into close competitions that
is a pretty large Advantage knowing that
the stones typically are going to be the
tiebreaker it is a market event that if
you can train it and be proficient in it
there are additional dividends to be had
in these tight situations at the top
awesome well let's move on to some other
very to another very strong woman
although she's not a strong woman
although I'm sure she could compete and
do quite well Laura horth out of Hungary
showing her chops not only as the
reigning fittest woman on earth and
Invitational Champion where she
accomplished the rare feat of beating
Tia Clair Tumi by the way uh Laura
horbath pretty darn good weightlifter
one Hungarian National weightlifting
championships in her weight division uh
went five for six so made all three
snatch attempts two out of three clean
and jerks missed her first cleaning jerk
due to lockout Phil let's talk a little
bit about about that what kind of weight
did she lift what body weight category
did uh she compete in because I can go
down the weightlifting rabbit hole and I
can nerd out but instead of me Diet
triing why don't you take it for a
second and then you know I'll do my
weird weightlifting nerd thing yeah
before you nerd out I'll just give the
stats on what Horath accomplished yes
she went five for six she was competing
in the 76 kgam weight class her 120 kgr
cleaning jerk was a Hungarian National
Record that she set at this event she
actually bested her own previous record
by three kilograms so that's a big deal
she uh totaled 2115 kilograms or 474
pounds to take the title in the 76
kilogram class over to you boom Phil
thank you one thing she did miss her
first clean J attempt due to lockout
wasn't an issue of the weight being
heavy it's just stricter judging
standard she came out came out and
smashed uh two heavier weights so like
not an issue it it was it was pretty
clear that like she missed it on more of
a like the technique was just slightly
offer that lift more so than the weight
being out of her range you know she had
she had lifted more than that previously
it was clear 114 was just it like her
almost like her safety attempt to like
get on and and guarantee a total because
she then increased it on both the
following attempts and hit them so yeah
yeah I mean look Laura horth great
lifter
and it's interesting because the main
thing that I hear when you watch top
CrossFit athletes compete in
weightlifting and I've seen this right
like I remember when some of the
Icelandic crossed athletes competed at
the world weightlifting Championship
right or they've done that a couple
different times you see that like
they're they get really antsy like
they're taking too much rest right
because they might have you know 10
minutes between attempts depending on
the size of the competition right so
they're like okay I want to go back out
there I want to go back out there and
one thing that works against them is
that they have a Time
between attempts right they're they're
they're used to getting their heart
rates up and they're used to trying you
know attempts like in very close
proximity back toback so it's always
interesting to see that to see how like
they get affected by the things that
should give them Advantage right like
for crossfitters a disadvantage is more
rest sometimes I want to also point
something out because I
remember not too long ago when a 200 lb
statch was basically Unthinkable for a
female cross said athlete and I
remember it was over 10 years
ago but I remember when Lindsay Valena a
CrossFit competitor out of California
who actually did Podium at the CrossFit
games when she snatched 200 pounds on
camera it was a Monumental Monumental
feat in the sport of CrossFit and by the
way she pressed out the weight like like
it would not have it would not have
flown in weightlifting competition it
was like a double press out right but
she snatched 200 pounds on camera it was
posted uh I think we have the video that
is posted on the official CrossFit
YouTube page it was such a big deal that
like CrossFit promoted it it was like
wow crossfitters can be strong too a
woman in CrossFit can snatch 200 pounds
that's like pedestrian compared to what
some of these women are lifting now now
that's still a heavy weight to snatch
right that is still a heavy weight to
snatch and not every CrossFit games not
every woman at the CrossFit Games can
snatch 200 pounds but it is certainly
not the maximum that you're going to see
athletes at the CrossFit games list
Horvath like she eclipsed that on her
second attempt in competition T Clair
Tumi we see her going heavier than that
frequently right like I bet t t Tumi
might be able to power snatch 90 kilos
or two roughly 200 pounds at this point
it's just interesting to me how much the
bar has been pushed oh that was a bad
pun when it comes to strength standards
in CrossFit yeah I would also add to
that that the going into the large
events whether it's the CrossFit Gams
the Rog imitational you it's pretty
common to see now that there is going to
be a match strength event what that will
be is UN unknown ahead of time but it
might be a cleaning Jerk it might be a
deadlift it might be a snatch and what
you had said before where each athlete
when they're doing that in the rounds
that they're doing it in they don't get
as much rest as you might get in a
sanctioned weightlifting competition so
like yeah they're more accustomed to not
only lifting heavy but lifting heavy
heavy in a shorter time frame against a
wider field uh after like you know
competing for two and a half days
already totally well let's move on to
strength but in a different form Russell
Orie squatting heavy we're used to that
but what we're a little out of practice
with is Russell ore competing at the
international level in this format right
we we Russell he is a uh he's a two-time
ipf world
champion but we haven't seen him compete
a l right he won it I believe 2019 and
2021 uh and he's been taking a break
brussel's got a lot going on he's a
businessman he's a gym owner there's a
lot going on uh but he has announced
recently he wants to return to
competition he clearly wants to win a
third world title and his squat here uh
Phil what does this squat signify to you
give us a rundown of what he did yeah so
uh or he actually hit 22 kilograms over
his ipf world record squat for a double
in training squatted raw of 342 half
kilogram uh squat which is 755 PBS
that's 22 kilos over his current world
record that still stands in the 83
kilogram class now we don't know what
his body weight was for this lift which
matters right very significant he's
probably heavier he's you know he still
has time before he competes in 2024 but
the fact that he did this for a double
is what is signifying to me that when he
comes back in 2024 and competes that
he's going to still be in my mind the
athlete to be in at 83 kilograms and I
think that this is just the market
trajectory we know he wants to compete
at the world games in 2025 where power
liting will make its debut so in order
to get there he has to qualify for it
the way that he does that is he competes
in 2024 I fully expect that to happen I
just think he will find success in 2024
to compete in 2025 I would be surprised
if that doesn't happen so not quite the
shocking like Underdog Story here I
think it's like the front runner going
to prove prove that why he's the front
runner but uh yeah this this particular
double is indicative to me that he's
still on top of his game and when he
comes back in 2024 that we should expect
impressive lifts if not rewriting
history books if I could squat like
anyone I would consider like if I could
just pick my body to move like anyone in
the squat Russell Ori might be it for me
I just want to give a special shout out
to Russell because like I will watch his
squat videos and I'll just get those
Instagram real rewatch counts coming up
because I'm like wow that looked really
good I wish I wish I could move like
that right it doesn't look effortless
but he looks locked in he looks stable
and it's just kind of like an ideal
squat I don't know this just me
fanboying a little bit right shout out
to Russell ory also a friend of the
brand also been on the barbin
podcast let's talk
Tempo Phil when you hear the word Tempo
in strength training what ises that
evoke for you let's still a little like
Roar Shack verbal Roar Shack image here
right what do you think when you hear
Tempo when I hear Tempo these days when
I hear Tempo because uh my engine sucks
I just uh you know instinctively hear
metcon and freak out uh so but when it
when it comes to uh putting a barbell in
your hand I Tempo I understand to be uh
how long you take for each rep and
timing each rep whether it's two seconds
up one second down etc
etc and Alex polish who by the sorry Dr
Alex polish because Alex has a
PHD wrote a great article for barbend
really breaking down Tempo and I think
there is a little bit of mythbusting
when it comes to Tempo Tempo is
controlling multiple aspects of the
speed of the lift in different phases of
the lift when you look at the top
athletes especially in the sport of
powerlifting virtually all of them are
doing some kind of tempo training and
when you look at the top athletes in
bodybuilding virtually all of them are
doing some kind of tempo Based training
and what that signifies is that to
really unlock in immense strength gains
and also hypertrophy gains Tempo
training is something that nearly every
athlete in my
anecdotal experience every athlete at
the top of the strength game at the top
of the aesthetic physique game they're
all using it what does that mean it
means that this is really important and
if you're not utilizing Tempo training
you're leaving a lot on the table both
when it comes to strength and when it
comes to hypertrophy I was going to say
a lot of the recent research is showing
for hypertrophy gains uh that uh
training in the lengthened position uh
for a longer periods of time is a way to
uh further promote hypertrophy uh
effectively so for Tempo training let's
say you you slow your Tempo down in the
lengthened portion of a of a rep and if
you do that over time Recent research
has shown that training in the
lengthened position is very good at
promoting hypertrophy so if that's what
you're looking for in terms of packing
on size that's where the research is
let's say you don't even care about
packing on size I care about packing on
size let say you don't care about that
say you're a powerlifter and you're not
worried about packing on size you're
just carry you're worried about your
total right Tempo training is a
fantastic way to identify weak points in
your lifts and to work through sticking
points right deadlift is a great example
some people have different sticking
points for some folks it's off the
ground like under their shins for some
folks it's toward the top Tempo training
is a really great way especially if
you're working with a coach uh who can
program tempo in a way that's going to
help you focus on your weaknesses and
bust through those sticking points right
so please if you are interested in
unlocking strength gains or hypertrophy
gains and or hypertrophy gains please
read Alex's article Dr Alex polish on
Barb ben.com love Alex's writing you're
going to enjoy it and we link it below
and we linked it in a card here so you
don't have any excuse right Tempo
training here's another thing I want to
point out about Tempo training I've been
traveling a lot Phil it's the holidays
family stuff other stuff I've been doing
a lot of body weight workouts you know
how you get more out of body weight
workouts
sometimes Tempo Tempo push-ups and Tempo
body weight squats I know it seems
simple I know everyone's like oh I'm
strong I don't need that let me tell
you you you want to be humbled you want
to be
sore you want to put your muscles to the
test you want to get a good workout
Tempo push-ups ask the friend who likes
you least to program a Tempo push-up and
body weight squat workout for you and
then come say body weight training
doesn't do anything you know that might
be the biggest like the most reasonable
selling point to like learn how to
properly Tempo train is for exactly that
sort of thing if you're like you're on
the road you're in a hotel you don't
have access to good equipment like
that's the way to get in the workout
that's the way to do it yeah 100 100%
right like it is who who actually you
know what folks can even if you respond
in the comments I will give you some of
the tempo training Hotel workouts that I
have developed in my weird little mind
so if people ask in the comments I will
respond so that's your strength tip of
the week here at strength weekly
Phil it's December we only have one
month left of Juicy 2023 strength
goodness but we're gonna bring every
we're gonna bring it to everyone here on
strength weekly we're going to bring it
to all of you on Barb ben.com if you
want to learn more also about hotel
workouts we got articles on that we
recently wrapped up the uh end of the
ifbb pro calendar uh Pro shows for 2023
uh so those are going to hit the docket
in the next uh week or week and a half
or so so uh a lot of action still coming
on even though we're in the holiday
season and uh you know make sure that
you uh learn how to Tempo train folks
for bar.com I'm David Thomas toow joined
by the
incomparable Phil Blackman thank you all
for tuning in we'll catch you next
[Music]
week